Finding aid to the Ruth Swan Clark Papers CA.MS.00147
Smith College Archives
Ruth Swan Clark Papers
1905-1949
Smith College Archives
Clark, Ruth Swan, 1887-
CA.MS.00147
0.625 linear feet (2 containers)
Class of 1909 and Professor of Psychology. Collection contains biographical material, correspondence, a personal diary, photographs, newspaper clippings, academic materials and publications.
Biographical / Historical
Ruth Swan Clark was a member of the class of 1909 at Smith College. In 1913, a few years after her graduation, she worked at Smith as an instructor in the Philosophy Department. She held this position until 1916, and in 1917 was promoted to Assistant Professor. In 1918, Clark found employment at the School for Social Work at Smith. She traveled away from Northampton in 1919 to earn her PhD in psychology from Columbia University. While in New York City, she worked as the psychologist for the Vocational Service for Juniors, a program that encouraged career counseling in public schools. She returned to Smith in 1922 when she accepted a position of Associate Professor in the Psychology Department. In 1929, she agreed to edit and publish the theories of her colleague in the Philosophy Department, Professor Harry Gardiner. She worked until 1934, compiling and recording his thoughts on human nature and other psychological phenomena. In 1943, Clark took on a job at the Howard Relief Society, a privately endowed charity, as their Executive Secretary. Here she worked raising money on behalf of school children who were under-privileged. Later, in 1949, Ruth became the Chairman of the Social Service Committee in the American Association for University Women. She also served on the Housing Committee of the League of Women Voters. Also in 1949, Clark was asked to write a complete history of the Psychology Department at Smith College. It was teaching in this department when she met her husband, J.T. Metcalf, also a Psychology professor. They had two daughters and one son together.
Scope and Contents
This collection includes biographical materials, correspondence, a personal diary, photographs, newspaper clippings, academic materials and publications regarding Clark's education and career at Smith College and elsewhere.
Related Material
Class of 1909 Records
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The materials in the Ruth Swan Clark papers came to the College Archives from a number of sources.
Clark, Ruth Swan, 1887-
- Biography, 1908-1949 (Box 718, Folder 1)
- Correspondence-American Book Company, 1934 (Box 718, Folder 2)
- Correspondence-Taylor, William S., 1929-1934 (Box 718, Folder 3)
- Diary, 1907 (Box 718, Folder 4)
- Education-Columbia University, 1917 (Box 718, Folder 5)
- Employment-Smith College, 1906-1949 (Box 718, Folder 6)
- Employment-Vocational Service for Juniors, 1919-1922 (Box 718, Folder 7)
- Photographs, 1905-1909 (Box 718, Folder 8)
- Publications-Ruth Swan Clark, 1922-1942 (Box 718, Folder 9)
- Publications-Type Scripts, undated (Box 718, Folder 10)
- Mss. Gardiner, Harry N., undated (Box 718.1, Folder 1)
- Mss. Gardiner, Harry N., undated (Box 718.1, Folder 2)
- Page Proof, 1937 (Box 718.1, Folder 3)
- Editing Rules-Manuscript, undated (Box 718.1, Folder 4)